BASED ON THE MANGA BY MAKOTO YUKIMURA
(幸村誠原著漫畫改編)
Einar, Thorfinn, from today you two will be friends.
埃納爾、托爾芬 你們就從今天開始做朋友吧
Come on, introduce yourselves.
來吧,互相介紹一下
I'll have you two work on the same job. Cooperate with each other, okay?
我會安排你們兩個負責同一份工作 要互相合作喔,好嗎?
Nice to meet you, Thorfinn.
很高興認識你,托爾芬
Hello.
你好
All right. Let me explain about the job.
好的,我跟你說明一下這份工作吧
Einar, what does this look like to you?
埃納爾,你覺得這看起來像什麼?
Um...
呃...
Is it a forest?
是森林嗎?
That's not quite right.
不太正確
This is a future wheat field.
這是未來的麥田
This forest belongs to me.
這座森林是我的
But I will lease it to you two.
但我會租借給你們兩個
- Lease? - Yes.
-租借? -對
I'll leave everything to you.
其他的事就交給你們囉
Clear the land, manage it, and harvest the crop.
整地、管理、收割
I will buy that from you at a proper rate.
我會用合理的價格買下你們的收成
When your earnings surpass the price at which you were bought,
當你們的盈餘 超過了你們當初的賣身價
buy yourselves out.
就把自己贖回來吧
Buy ourselves? You mean... we can become free?
把自己贖回來? 你的意思是...我們能夠重獲自由?
Yes, that's right.
對,沒錯
Use your own power and the right procedure to become free.
利用自己的力量和正確的方式 讓自己重獲自由
Depending on how hard you work,
端看你們工作得多勤奮
you can do so within three years.
你們三年內就能夠完成這件事
I won't charge you the lease payment until your first harvest.
在你們首度收成之前 我不會向你們收租
What's wrong? Do you disapprove?
怎麼了嗎?你不同意嗎?
No! Thank you! I will do my best.
不是,謝謝你,我會盡力而為
If there are any problems or you have any questions,
如果有任何麻煩或者有任何疑問
ask Pater.
都可以問帕特
He knows the farm very well.
他很了解這座農場
Nice to meet you.
很高興認識你
I bought my freedom in the same way.
我就是用這種方式重獲自由的
I know it's tough being in a foreign land but do your best.
我知道在異國的土地上會很辛苦 你們就盡力而為吧
Yes!
好
Just watch how Thorfinn works for today.
今天就觀察托爾芬怎麼做就好
You must be tired from the long trip.
長途跋涉來到這裡一定累壞了
Thorfinn, take care of Einar, okay?
托爾芬,好好照顧埃納爾,好嗎?
- Got it? - Yes.
-可以嗎? -好
Hey, is the master... What?
嘿,這位主人...什麼?
Hey, wait a second.
嘿,等等我
Hey, what kind of person is the master?
嘿,主人是什麼樣的人啊?
Is this normal in Denmark?
這在丹麥很常見嗎?
There were slaves in my homeland too,
我的家鄉也有奴隸
but slaves were always slaves.
但一日奴隸,終身奴隸
I was born in the north of England.
我出生在北英格蘭
What about you?
你呢?
Iceland.
冰島
Iceland, huh?
冰島?
Iceland is...
冰島...
where?
在哪裡?
Wow... You cut down quite a lot already.
哇,你已經砍下了好多棵樹
How much more to go?
還得再砍多少?
All of this side.
這邊全部
This side?
這邊?
You see that river?
你看到河流了嗎?
Everything on this side of the river.
河流這一側所有的樹
On this side of the river?
河流的這一側?
That means...
那就是說...
we still have quite a lot to do?
要砍的樹還有很多?
What?
搞什麼?
What is it?
你幹嘛?
Didn't he tell you to just watch?
他不是叫你觀察就好嗎?
I want to be free as soon as possible. Is that wrong?
我想儘早重獲自由,這也錯了嗎?
In that case, do me a favor and choose a tree farther away.
這樣的話,請你幫個忙 選一棵離這裡遠一點的樹
Also, cut it so that it falls perpendicular to the river.
還有,你在砍樹的時候 要確保樹倒下的方向跟河流垂直
I see.
我懂了
We're transporting them using the river?
我們要用河來運送樹幹?
I'm so hungry.
我好餓喔
How does lunch work here?
午餐要怎麼處理?
They serve it.
他們會提供
That's great. Do we go somewhere to get it?
太棒了,我們要去哪裡領取嗎?
No, a farmhand should deliver it soon.
不用,農場幫手 應該馬上就會送過來了
Are you serious? What great service.
真的假的?服務也太好了吧
- No way! - I'm serious!
-怎麼可能? -我說的是真的
Our food! Isn't that right, Thorfinn?
食物來了!對吧,托爾芬?
I'm serious. You're the only one who hasn't done it.
我是認真的 你是唯一一個沒去過的人
I had no clue! Maybe I'll go tonight then.
我完全不知道,或許我今晚該去瞧瞧
Yeah, go ahead. And get dumped.
好啊,快去,然後就會被拋棄
Come on!
幹嘛這樣啦?
Hey, isn't that the newbie?
嘿,他不是那個新來的嗎?
Seems like it.
似乎是
What a dumb face. Fitting for a slave.
一臉傻樣,就像個奴隸
Hello, I'm...
你們好,我...
- We know. We heard. - Um...
-我們知道,我們聽說了 -呃...
- What's this? - Your lunch.
-這是什麼? -你們的午餐
All right, tonight's the night.
好囉,今晚有好戲看了
Um, is this...
呃,這是...
Like I said, it's your lunch.
我說過了,是你們的午餐
This measly thing?
這麼寒酸的東西?
What? Do you have a problem with that?
怎樣?你有什麼問題嗎?
Well, it's more like...
呃,這比較像是...
This is for two people?
這是兩人份的量?
- Did you hear him? - Jeez...
-你聽到他說了什麼嗎? -真是的
Hey, is this your first job as a slave?
嘿,這是你第一次當奴隸嗎?
Yeah.
對
Then remember this. You're lucky to even get food.
那你記住了,能有食物就要偷笑了
And we free people came all the way here to drop off lunch.
我們這些自由人 大老遠地送飯過來給你
The first thing you should do is say thank you.
你第一句該說的話是“謝謝你”
These guys...
這些人...
Come on, say it.
快點,說吧
"Thank you very much."
”十分感謝你”
What's with those eyes, you brat?
你這個臭小子 你那眼神是什麼意思?
I'll take this. Thank you very much.
我們收下了,十分感謝你們
Teach that guy some manners, Thorfinn.
托爾芬,教他一些禮數
Also, don't hurt the horse.
還有,別讓馬受傷了
Yes.
好
They're taking a nap...
他們在睡午覺...
What's up with them? They just came to play hooky.
他們是怎麼搞的?來這裡偷懶
You too...
你也是...
Stop kissing up to them just because you're a slave.
不要因為你是個奴隸 就對他們低聲下氣
Einar, push it from the back.
埃納爾,從後面推
I'll pull it from the front.
我會從前面拉
Once we get to the bank, we'll make a raft.
到了河岸之後,我們來造木筏
Shouldn't we cut this wood a little more?
我們不需要再把 這塊木頭砍掉一些嗎?
It's impossible with just one old horse.
只有一匹老馬是不可能辦到的
The trees belong to the master. We can't cut them without permission.
樹都是主人的 沒有他的允許,我們不能亂砍
Hey, isn't this supposed to be their job?
嘿,這不該是他們的工作嗎?
They don't usually let slaves handle horses.
他們通常不會讓奴隸碰馬匹
- And why is there only one old horse? - Whatever, let's get to it.
-而且為什麼只有一匹老馬? -算了啦,我們開始吧
- Einar! - Right!
-埃納爾 -來了
Einar, lift the front part.
埃納爾,去前面把樹幹抬高
Got it!
好的
Let's go.
走吧
I'm so hungry I feel nauseous.
我餓到想吐
I'll never forgive those guys.
我絕對不會饒過那些人
How dare they eat my lunch.
他們竟敢吃掉我的午餐
Hands are basically people who have no choice but to work for the master
幫手基本上別無選擇 只能幫主人做事
because they don't have their own land, right?
因為他們沒有自己的土地,對吧?
Yeah.
對
What the heck!
搞什麼鬼?
That's the same as being half enslaved!
這跟半奴隸有什麼兩樣?
They're bullying us just to feel assured that there are people below them.
他們欺負我們只是為了 確認有人身分比他們更低罷了
Thorfinn! You think so too, right?
托爾芬,你也這麼認為,對吧?
I don't know.
我不知道
I couldn't care less about that.
我一點都不在乎
You have to care!
你必須在乎
We are the master's property!
我們是主人的財產
It's unacceptable for mere farmhands to exploit us.
區區的農場幫手想要剝屑我們 這完全令人無法接受
I'll tell the master.
我要告訴主人
Don't do that. It'll only make the harassment worse.
別那麼做,這樣只會讓他們變本加厲
You... You're okay with this?
你...竟然覺得無所謂?
- Einar, Thorfinn! - Master...
-埃納爾、托爾芬 -主人
Einar, what are your thoughts after spending a day here?
埃納爾,今天是你 在這裡的第一天,你有什麼感想?
- Um, I have to report-- - Stop it.
-那個,我得向您舉發... -別說了
Shut up! Excuse me, I have something to report.
住口,不好意思 我得向您舉發一件事
Today, the farmhands... that...
今天,那些農場幫手,他們...
What do you want to report, Einar?
埃納爾,你想舉發什麼?
What a strange man. If it's nothing, I'm going to get going.
真是個怪人啊 如果沒什麼事的話,我得走囉
Einar...
埃納爾...
You didn't need to report it?
你不想舉發了嗎?
Shut up.
閉嘴啦
- It's so hot today. - We've got water!
-今天好熱啊 -我們帶水來囉
It's fresh from the spring.
是新鮮的泉水喔
It's cold!
冰冰涼涼的喔
Give me a cup!
給我一杯
Quick turn!
急轉彎
- Here you go. - Thank you.
-請喝 -謝謝
We went to the deep spring this time.
我們這一次去到更深處的地方取泉水
I feel revived! Thank you.
有如重生,謝謝你們
- You're welcome. - All right.
-不客氣 -嗯
Okay, everyone! We're almost there.
好了,各位,我們快完成了
- Let's finish this area before noon. - Yes, sir!
-在中午之前處理完這一區吧 -好的,主人
The master works himself, huh?
主人自己也會下田?
I always thought rich people didn't work.
我一直以為有錢人不用工作
When you see them working like this,
見到他們這樣工作的時候
there is no difference between the Danes and English.
就會覺得丹麥人 和英格蘭人之間並沒有什麼不同
Hey, you're doing it wrong!
唉喲,你做錯了
Don't make me repeat myself, Olmar.
別讓我再說一次,歐瑪
What the heck? I'm doing exactly what you told me to do.
搞什麼啊?我明明就照你說的做
Use a sickle.
用鐮刀
And you have to cut them below the knee.
而且收割高度必須在膝蓋以下
I've already told you this!
我已經告訴過你了
- It doesn't even matter how you cut them. - What!
-怎麼割根本沒差好嗎? -你說什麼?
You fool! Once the wheat is done, we have to pasture the animals.
笨蛋,小麥收割之後 我們會進行放牧
We leave more stubble so we can feed it to the livestock later.
我們要留下更多的殘株 才能夠餵食牲畜
You are already 17 years old and you still don't know the process.
你已經17歲了,還是搞不清楚流程
That's why you can't understand the significance of each step.
所以你也就不會明白 每個階段的重要性
Enough already... I know all of that.
夠了啦,那些我都知道
I've got the process down perfectly.
每個步驟我都執行得很完美
Show more humility when someone's talking to you!
當別人在跟你說話的時候 你該謙虛一點
As someone with authority--
我有權跟你說這些...
Okay, okay! Below the knee, right?
好啦...膝蓋以下,對嗎?
Understood!
知道了啦
You fool! What is with that swing!
你這個笨蛋,幹嘛亂揮?
You're going to damage the ears of wheat!
你會讓麥穗受損
- You said below the knee! - What is going on?
-你說了要在膝蓋以下 -這是怎麼回事?
He's getting yelled at like crazy.
他被吼得太慘了吧
He's Olmar, the master's son.
他是歐瑪,主人的兒子
Oh, they're father and son...
噢,他們是父子喔
I can't take this anymore!
我再也受不了了
For once I decide to help you out, but all you do is nitpick on the details.
我好不容易答應幫你忙 你卻一直在吹毛求疵
I'm done. I was going to work, but never mind.
我不幹了 我本來是想好好工作,但算了吧
Hey! Where do you think you're going, Olmar?!
喂,你要給我去哪裡,歐瑪?
Away from you, you old man!
離你遠遠的,臭老頭
In time, you will be inheriting this farm.
你遲早要繼承這座農場
Act more responsibly.
拿出一些責任感吧
When did I ever ask you to let me inherit it!
我什麼時候叫你把這座農場交給我?
I'm a grown man! I don't have time to be doing teeny-tiny
我是個大人,沒空跟你在田裡做這些
insignificant jobs out in the field!
不重要的芝麻小事
I'm going to use this...
我要用這把...
Huh?
怎麼搞的?
- Hey, what is he doing? - I wonder...
-他想幹嘛? -誰知道...
I'll rise up the ranks with this sword!
我要用這把劍力爭上游
- Damn it! - Olmar! Wait, you little...
-該死 -歐瑪,等等,你這個臭小子
Very soon, I am going to England. I swear.
我很快就會前往英格蘭,我發誓
I'm not going to spend my whole life out in these boondocks.
我才不要一輩子待在這個窮鄉僻壤
I'm going to enlist in Prince Canute's army
我要加入庫奴特王子的兵團
and make a name for myself!
讓自己揚名立萬
Um...
呃...
Young master, how soon is "very soon"?
少主,”很快”是多快?
Very soon means very soon.
很快就是很快的意思
In time, King Harald will convene a fleet for reinforcements.
到時,哈羅德國王將召集增援艦隊
I think it would be best for you to take over this farm.
我覺得留在這座農場對你比較好
Huh? You too? What do you know anyway?
什麼?連妳也這麼說? 妳又懂什麼了?
No, I mean...
不是啦,我意思是...
I'm just so worried.
我只是很擔心
Hey...
嘿...
Let's do it one more time...
我們再做一次吧
Yes! Good job, my daughter!
太好了,幹得好,我的乖女兒
- Keep it up. - How is it going?
-再加把勁 -一切還好嗎?
I brought a meal for the young master.
我替少主送食物來了
Not now. They're about to start round two.
現在不是時候 他們正要展開第二回合
Oh, my! Oh, my...
我的天...
Anyway, now our family has nothing to worry about.
總之,我們家現在不用愁啦
That's right.
說得好
As long as the young master continues to favor her...
只要少主一直寵幸她...
What is the matter, young master?
少主,怎麼了嗎?
Did our daughter do something to upset you?
我們的女兒惹您不開心了嗎?
Shut up, you idiot!
閉嘴,妳這個笨蛋
I know what you're all up to. You poor tenant farmers!
我很清楚你們在打什麼主意 你們這些窮佃農
You're after my dad's fortune.
你們都在覬覦我爸的財產
You want to become relatives of the Ketil family and live lavishly!
你們都想跟凱特爾家族結成親家 一輩子享有榮華富貴
We've never thought about that!
我們從來沒有這樣想過
You women are always like this!
妳們女人就是這個德性
Young master! That was not our intention!
少主,那不是我們的本意
Young master, please wait!
少主,請留步
Damn it! Damn all of you!
該死,你們全都該死
I'm my own person! Not a freebie that's attached to my dad!
我是自己的主人 又不是我爸身邊的免費贈品
Damn it! This is unbearable!
該死,真令人無法忍受
Oh, it's the young master.
噢,是少主
What? Young master?
什麼?少主?
- Young master! - Hey!
-少主 -嘿
What are you doing?
你在做什麼?
- It's dangerous to be riding at night. - Dangerous!
-晚上騎馬很危險 -很危險的
And what are you two doing?
你們兩個又是在幹什麼?
We'll be right there
我們立刻過去
Come on, use your feet.
快點,用你的腳
You know, we went to see that woman
是說,我們去找那個女人
but the farmhands got there before us.
但農場幫手搶先我們一步
Hey, the wheat...
喂,小麥...
But if we get in a fight with them
但如果我們跟他們打起來
our boss will get mad at us again.
主人又會對我們發脾氣
- It's ridiculous, you know? - Ridiculous!
-太可笑了,你知道嗎? -可笑至極
Must be nice to be you.
能夠跟你一樣就好了
You're free to do whatever you want on this farm.
你可以隨心所欲地 在這座農場做你想做的事
Shut up. You wouldn't know how I feel.
閉嘴,你們才不明白我的感受
Oh, are you mad? Are you? Is something bothering you?
噢,你生氣囉?是嗎? 你有什麼煩惱嗎?
Don't be mad!
不要生氣啦
I don't have any time to waste on you two.
我沒時間在這裡跟你們耗
Go back to the fort and go to sleep.
回去堡壘睡覺吧
Now, now... Don't be so prickly.
唉呀呀...別這麼敏感嘛
- You're still young. - You're so cold.
-你還年輕 -你還真冷漠
Hey, don't grab onto the muzzle.
喂,別抓著口套
Don't worry. Let's just get some more drinks.
別擔心啦,我們再去喝幾杯吧
Let's talk the night away, young master.
我們聊個通宵吧,少主
Tell us about your worries as a youth.
跟我們說說年輕人的煩惱吧
You just want to be entertained by my stories!
你們只是想拿我的故事尋開心而已
Don't be ridiculous! I'm leaving! Let go!
別開玩笑了,我要走了,放手
Why can't he just inherit it without complaining...?
為什麼他就不能乖乖地繼承呢?
He doesn't know war.
他不知道戰爭是什麼
He's under the impression that warriors are cool.
他只是以為戰士很酷
People who fight wars are all animals.
踏上戰場的人全都是野獸
Go to sleep. We have an early morning tomorrow.
快睡吧,明天一大早就要起床
In the past, the village where I lived
我住的那個村落曾經
was attacked by soldiers twice.
被士兵攻擊過兩次
The army sent by the King of England
英格蘭國王派來的軍隊
burnt down all the houses in the village.
把村裡的房子全都燒毀了
My dad fought back, but he was killed.
我爸反擊了,但也被殺了
I...
我...
couldn't do anything but watch.
只能眼睜睜地看著這一切
The second time
第二次
was by Danish soldiers.
是丹麥的士兵
They said they were rescuing us from the tyrannical King of England.
他們說要解救我們 脫離殘暴的英格蘭國王
But they just plundered the entire village.
但他們只是掠奪了整個村莊
They're disguised as humans, but they're nothing
他們佯裝成人類,但實際上
but animals.
卻是禽獸
Hey, Thorfinn...
嘿,托爾芬
Did you fall asleep?
你睡著了嗎?
"Snake."
蛇
Subtitle translation by:
字幕翻譯:歐德慧